Finding Aid for the Ralph Nelson Papers LSC.0875
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Paintings, Photographs, and Pictorial Materials
  - Portrait photographs. (Box 97, Box 98, Box 99)
    Jackie Gleason.
    Charlton Heston.
    Marlene Dietrich.
    Leslie Howard.
    Richard Whorf.
    Maximillion Schell.
  - Photographs. (Box 136)
    Many from Playhouse 90 productions.
  - Photographs - Exteriors, Set Design. (Box 138)
    Cafe exteriors.
    Apartment interiors.
    Bistro sketches.
  - Photographs., (1 envelope) (Box 138)
    Flight of the doves.
  - Photographs. (Box 138)
  - Photographs - Soldier Blue., (2 items) (Box 140)
  - Exterior photographs of Paris. (Box 140)
  - Paris - exterior photos., 1963 (Box 141)
  - Photographs - Details., 1963 (Box 142)
    Hotels, beauty parlors, markets, etc.
  - Pictorial Materials
    - Sketch for Justice designed by Albert Heschong., (Photographic copy) (Box 22)
    - Aladdin., (Facsimile) (Box 90)
      18 costume sketches by Irene Sharoff.
    - Original architectural renderings (4) for Once a Thief. (Box 90)
    - Tear sheets for various productions. (Box 45)
    - Play bill for Pygmalion., (Framed) (Box 97, Box 98, Box 99)
    - Ad layouts for various motion pictures. (Box 97, Box 98, Box 99)
    - Mounted promotional kits: (Box 97, Box 98, Box 99)
      Hamlet.
      Aladdin.
      This Happy Breed.
      Junior Miss.
    - "Hamlet" set sketches. Dupont Show of the Month., (Reproductions) (Box 97, Box 98, Box 99)
    - Original production sketches. (Box 97, Box 98, Box 99)
      What About Linda.
    - Artist's renderings (2) of interior chapel scenes from Counterpoint. (Box 147)
    - Father Goose Original production sketch. (Box 147)
    - Once a Thief Billboard poster. (Box 147)
    - Duel at Diablo art work., (Reproduction) (Box 147)
    - Mounted portrait of Charlton Heston. (Box 147)
    - Oil portrait of Colonel F.U. Foster, by Yvonne Wood., (Framed) (Box 93)
    - Posters. (Box 138)
    - 3 Large Posters. (Box 147)
      The Wrath of God Logo (1).
      Tick...tick...tick... (2).
    - Sketches & drawings of Paris exteriors. (Box 140)
    - Fortune Cookie - Sketches & drawings., 1966 (Box 142)
- Set Models
  - The church in Counterpoint., (Approximately 14 × 12 × 7", made of cardboard and wood) (Box 94)
- Production Files
  - Flight of the Doves Production Files (Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51)
    - A - C. (Box 47)
    - C (continued) - E. (Box 48)
    - F - L. (Box 49)
    - M - S. (Box 50)
    - S (continued) - Z. (Box 51)
  - Tick...Tick...Tick.. Production Files (Box 52, Box 53, Box 54)
    - A - L. (Box 52)
    - M - S. (Box 53)
    - S (continued) - Z. (Box 54)
  - Soldier Blue Production Files (Box 56, Box 57, Box 58, Box 59)
    - A - C. (Box 56)
    - C (continued) - M. (Box 56)
    - M (continued) - P. (Box 57)
    - P (continued) - S. (Box 58)
    - S (continued) - Z. (Box 59)
  - Complete Producer's Files for The Wrath of God (Box 81, Box 82, Box 83, Box 84, Box 85, Box 86, Box 87, Box 88)
    Starring Robert Mitchum
    Produced - Written - Directed by Ralph Nelson
    (for Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer)
    Of special interest to the study of film production.
    The film was prepared in London and Los Angeles, filmed entirely in Mexico with post-production work done in Los Angeles. The files include reports on Mexican technicians, censorship in Mexico and regulations of the Sindicado, the Mexican technician's union.
    Four writers were involved in developing the screenplay in various versions, and all treatments and drafts are included, as well as the Writer's Guild Arbitration, which finally gave to Ralph Nelson sole credit as the writer. This is unusual, since the Writer's Guild is reluctant to give a producer or director any screen credit.
    The catalogue of the files is attached.
    - Accounting. (Box 81)
    - Accounting for Location Survey. (Box 81)
    - Advertising (Sales, Promotion, Publicity MGM). (Box 81)
    - Arbitration (Writer's Guild Credits). (Box 81)
    - Aubrey, James - Memos. (Box 81)
    - B/Wk and Cash Summary. (Box 81)
    - Breakdown Sheets. (Box 81)
    - Budget Daily Progress Reports. (Box 81)
    - Budget Information. (Box 81)
      Complete Breakdown, American and Mexican including all departments and correspondence.
    - Call Sheets (American). (Box 82)
    - Call Sheets (Mexican). (Box 82)
    - Camera Reports (American). (Box 82)
    - Camera Reports (Mexican). (Box 82)
    - Customs, (American and Mexican). (Box 82)
    - Casting. (Box 82)
    - Censorship, Script Approval (Mexico). (Box 82)
    - Continuity Script. (Box 82)
    - Cost Trial Runs (Weekly). (Box 82)
    - Credits. (Box 83)
    - Daily Progress Reports. (Box 83)
    - Day Out of Days for Actors. (Box 83)
    - Editing. (Box 83)
    - Electric. (Box 83)
    - End of Picture Sale. (Box 83)
    - Equipment. (Box 83)
    - Expenses. (Box 83)
    - Extras Report. (Box 83)
    - General. (Box 83)
    - General (M.G.M.). (Box 83)
    - Hotel Accomodations. (Box 83)
    - Insurance. (Box 83)
    - Insurance Claim (Wrecked Prop Truck). (Box 83)
    - Insurance Claim (Ken Hutchison, Actor). (Box 83)
    - Inter-Office Memos. (Box 83)
    - Invoices. (Box 83)
    - Kodak Mexicana. (Box 84)
    - Locations. (Box 84)
    - Location Photographs and 1927 Lincoln. (Box 84)
    - Looping - Daily Production Reports. (Box 84)
    - Main Titles and End Credits. (Box 84)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence. (Box 84)
    - Movement Orders (to Different Locations). (Box 84)
    - Music. (Box 84)
    - Office Supplies. (Box 84)
    - Nicholas & Company (London Barristers for Rainbow). (Box 84)
    - Panavision. (Box 84)
    - Personnel. (Box 85)
    - Press Cuttings. (Box 85)
    - Previews. (Box 85)
    - Props. (Box 85)
    - Post Production. (Box 85)
    - Publicity. (Box 85)
    - Release Dates. (Box 85)
    - Research. (Box 85)
    - S.A.G. Contracts. (Box 85)
    - Samuelson's (London) Equipment. (Box 85)
    - Screenings. (Box 85)
    - Script Changes. (Box 85)
    - Script Correspondence. (Box 85)
    - Script Distribution. (Box 85)
    - Script Notes and Correspondence. (Box 85)
    - Script Rights. (Box 85)
    - Set Decorations. (Box 85)
    - Shipping. (Box 85)
    - Shooting Schedules. (Box 85)
    - Shooting Delays. (Box 86)
    - Sindicato (Mexican Union). (Box 86)
    - Tenicos Y Manuales. (Box 86)
    - Sound Effect Reports. (Box 86)
    - Special Effects. (Box 86)
    - Sterling Cost Breakdown (London Expenses). (Box 86)
    - Stills. (Box 86)
    - Story Board - Car Chase. (Box 86)
    - Stunt Adjustment Contracts. (Box 86)
    - Telegrams. (Box 86)
    - Television Version Notes. (Box 86)
    - Travel Orders. (Box 86)
    - Treatment Notes. (Box 86)
    - Unit - Staff and Personnel Orders. (Box 87)
    - Wardrobe. (Box 87)
    - Wardrobe Taken By Cast. (Box 87)
    - Weekly Production Costs. (Box 87)
    - Work Permits (Mexico). (Box 87)
    - Writers. (Box 87)
    - The Wrath of God. A novel by James Graham aka Harry Patterson (Box 87, Box 88)
      Scripts by various writers:
      - 1. By James Graham., January 28, 1971 (Box 87)
      - 2. By James Graham. Edited by Robin Karney Script Editor for Rainbow Productions., February 15, 1971 (Box 87)
      - 3. Screenplay by John Briley., April 30, 1971 (Box 87)
      - 4. Re-write and comments on Briley Script. (Box 87)
      - 5. Listed "First Draft Screenplay" by John Bril., June 1, 1971 (Box 87)
      - 6. 1st 30pp. submitted by Clair Huffaker., n.d. (Box 88)
      - 7. Full screenplay by Clair Huffaker., August 8, 1971 (Box 88)
      - 8. 1st 54pp. by Ralph Nelson., August 23, 1971 (Box 88)
      - 9. Full Screenplay by Ralph Nelson., n.d. (Box 88)
      - 10. First Draft Screenplay by Ralph Nelson., September 17, 1971 (Box 88)
      - 11. Rewritten Draft Screenplay by Ralph Nelson., October 18, 1971 (Box 88)
      - 12. Shooting Script Draft Screenplay by Ralph Nelson., November 3, 1971 (Box 88)
      - 13. Continuity Script Draft Screenplay by Ralph Nelson., July 2, 1972 (Box 88)
- "Motion Pictures"
  - Embryo (Box 72)
    General Correspondence.
    Deal Memos - Legal Agreements.
    Miscellaneous.
    Music Sheet.
    Research (Magazines, clippings, etc.).
    Stills.
    Script (4 versions including Director's shooting script with production notes).
  - The Wilby Conspiracy (Box 73)
    Legal Agreements - deal memos.
    Schedule.
  - Tick...tick...tick... (Box 73)
    Miscellaneous correspondence.
    Phil Gersh Agency.
  - Duel at Diablo (Box 73)
    Nelson/Engel correspondence.
  - Flight of the Doves (Box 74)
    Fran Roy Correspondence.
    Foster Bromhead.
    Frank Gabrielson.
    Nicholas & Company (Legal - John Elford).
    Brochures on Ireland.
    Location scouting correspondence.
    Irish correspondence.
    Stills (10 black & white photographs (12 × 15") in large manila envelope).
  - Soldier Blue (Box 75)
    Sketches from the story board for the massacre sequences (4 framed pictures).
  - Portrait of a Star - Miscellaneous. (Box 77)
  - Counterpoint (Freedman & Freedman) - Petty Cash and some correspondence. (Box 77)
- "Miscellaneous - Old Television Productions"
  - A Lion is in the Streets. (Box 77)
    Includes correspondence for a screenplay by Ralph Nelson for Cagney Productions.
  - The Big Wheel. (Box 77)
    Correspondence relating to a play written by Ralph Nelson. Optioned several times but never produced.
  - Cinderella. (Box 77)
    3 folders of general correspondence relating to the Rodgers & Hammerstein Special for CBS. A musical version of Cinderella written especially for television and directed by Ralph Nelson starring Julie Andrews, Howard Lindsey, Dorothy Stickney. Complete schedules, etc.
  - CBS Personal. (Box 77)
    Includes contracts from 1949-1957
  - CBS general correspondence., 1957-1960 (Box 77)
    Continuation of similar file. Relating to Ralph Nelson's contractual obligations to CBS.
  - "College." (Box 77)
    Correspondence with Dartmouth, Yale, and Western Reserve re scholarships offered to Ralph Nelson as a result of winning 3 National Theatre Conference Contests for playwriting.
  - Dog Suit. (Box 77)
    re a play called Man in the Dog Suit which was produced on Broadway starring Hume Cronyn and Jessica Tandy, directed by Ralph Nelson.
  - John Elliott., 1946-1955 (Box 77)
    This folder contains material of Mr. Elliott who represented Mr. Nelson as a writer from 1946-1955. The correspondence consists of letters regarding various productions of Mr. Nelson's plays and publications.
  - Guild. (Box 77)
    re the Radio and Television Directors Guild.
    It was originally the Radio Director's Guild, but with the expansion of television in 1949 it was enlarged to embrace television directors as well, and the name changed to the Radio and Television Directors Guild. Mr. Nelson was the first television director to become President of the Guild - later to be absorbed by The Director's Guild of America, embracing all Motion Picture Directors.
  - Climax shows. (Box 77)
    Folder of complete schedules. Climax was a popular melodramatic series for the CBS Television Network under Chrysler Corporation sponsorship. Several of these titles were later made into Motion Pictures. Mr. Nelson directed several and produced quite a number of them.
  - Theatre., early 1950s (Box 77)
    Correspondence between Mr. Nelson and various theatre personalities.
  - Theatre Wing. (Box 77)
    Correspondence with the American Theatre Wing when Ralph Nelson's services were called upon as a Guest Director.
    It is interesting to note that some of the students he taught at that time later achieved fame; such as Hal Holbrook.
  - Mama Correspondence. (Box 78)
  - Scripts of Mama., (4 vol.) (Box 78)
- Miscellaneous
  - Correspondence re The Hiroshima Maidens. (Box 20)
    This includes letters from Dick Powell and Norman Cousins.
  - Theatre programs (some autographed). (Box 45, Folder 1)
    For:
    Maude Adams.
    William Gilette.
    Mr. Forbes-Robertson.
    Gerald Dumaurier.
    Richard Mansfield.
    Alfred Lunt and Lynn Fontanne.
    Includes:
    Peter Pan.
    The Admirable Crichton.
    What Every Woman Knows, by James Barrie.
  - Rainbow Correspondence - General., 1962-1976; (Legal manila folder) (Box 79)
  - General Correspondence., 1966-1976; (Legal manila folder) (Box 79)
  - Correspondence - General pretaining to films., (Legal manila folder) (Box 79)
  - Rainbow Productions - Legal., (Legal manila folder) (Box 79)
  - Rainbow Productions - General., (Legal manila folder) (Box 79)
  - Ralph Nelson - Travel Itinerary., (2 legal manila folders) (Box 79)
  - V.A. Hospital Tour., 1972; (Legal manila folder) (Box 79)
  - Ralph Nelson Productions/Aurora., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
    Financial statements.
  - Ralph Nelson Productions/Aurora., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
  - Rogers & Cowan Publicists - Dale Olson., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
  - Rogers, Cowan, Brenner Incorporated., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
  - Moscow Film Festival - Bella Espstein., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
  - Pam, Jerry & Associates., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
  - Directors Guild of America., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
  - Moscow Film Festival., 1967; (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
  - Nelson/Engel., 1964-1966; (2 legal manila folders) (Box 80)
  - Nelson/Engel United Artists., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
    Financial agreement.
  - Ralph Nelson - Selmur Productions., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
    Expense vouchers.
  - Rainbow/Selmur., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
    Reimbursement.
  - Selmur Pictures Correspondence., (Legal manila folder) (Box 80)
  - Production material. (Box 104-106, 110, 112)
  - Scripts. (Box 111)
  - Correspondence. (Box 123)
  - Plaques. (Box 135)
  - Cartoons, posters, photographs. (Box 137)
  - Soldier Blue music cuts., (Audio tape) (Box 135)
  - Music - Listener's guides., (Photocopy) (Box 141)
  - Flight of the doves., (Slate clapper board) (Box 141)
- Addenda
  - Fate is the Hunter, Father Goose, and Soldier in the Rain. (Box 21, Box 22)
    All correspondence, business and general, including expenses, form letters, personal files, finances, censorship, legal, insurance, lists, research material, publicity, technical, pertaining to the productions of Fate is the Hunter, Father Goose, and Soldier in the Rain.
  - Correspondence and contracts between Mr. Nelson and Four Star Television. (Box 19)
    Including letters from Dick Powell, Steve Fisher, Milton Berle, Dale Wasserman, on the following projects:
    Three Soldiers by Dick Simmons.
    Goodbye Hannah by Steve Fisher.
    Alaska Solo by Gail Ingram.
    Medicine Man by Ann Bailey.
    The Loaner by Rod Serling.
  - Puzzle for Fanatics - original holographic story by Ralph Nelson. (Box 19)
    Never produced.
  - Correspondence re the Guggenheim Fellowship. (Box 19)
    With signed letters from Howard Lindsay, George Freedley, John T. Elliott.
  - Correspondence re the production of Hamlet., 1960 and v.d. (Box 19)
    With signed letters from Thomas Yoseloff, Ben Shahn, William L. Springer. Also, all correspondence between Mr. Nelson and CBS Television, breakdown of budget, breakdown of casting and shooting.
  - Correspondence re the production of Lady in a Cage., 1962 and v.d. (Box 19)
    With signed letters from Luther Davis, Jerry Wald, Joan Crawford. Also, the first budget breakdown, all contractual materials, first letters outlining details of financing (dated 1962).
  - Mister Doc - original typed script of CBS Television production., 1961 (Box 19)
    Also, budget breakdown, stills, original story idea.
  - Correspondence re National Theatre Conference., 1948 (Box 20)
    With signed letters from Hallie Flannigan (3), Walter Prichard Eaton (1), Lee Kazanoff (2).
  - Correspondence re the production of Requiem for a Heavyweight. (Box 20)
    With pertinent notes on David Susskind. Budget breakdown, contracts, publicity, finances, set design, and correspondence.
  - Correspondence re the production of The Wind is Ninety. (Box 20)
    With signed letters by John T. Elliott, Robert Sherwood, Roland Fernand, Richard Tucker. Contracts, budget breakdown.
  - Junior Miss. (Box 20)
    Including budget breakdown, production breakdown, correspondence, contracts.
  - Mail Call. (Box 20)
    Including correspondence, budget breakdown, production breakdown, contracts.
  - We're Ready. (Box 22)
    Production manual containing complete book score and parts.
  - Once a Thief. (Box 90)
    Five original pen and ink drawings.
  - Father Goose., 1964 (Box 9)
    Director's working copy with all holographic changes from inception of idea to final shooting script.
    This seems to be the same item in Boxes 9-10, under Father Goose.
  - Dixie! A play by Ralph Nelson., (Holographic copy) (Box 7)
  - The Diddy-Wah-Diddy, a novel by Ralph Nelson. (Box 7)
    Research material and written chapters.
  - Fate is a Hunter - Sketches., (93 items, photographic copies) (Box 23)